

an.nguyen@jhu.edu \(\subseteq +1\) 660-234-4266 in \(\link\text{linkedin.com/in/an-d-nguyen/}\) \(\hat{\text{https://annguyen0212.github.io}}\)

# **SUMMARY**

Cognitive scientist with a focus on human perception and cognitive processes. 5 years of experience in experimental designs and data analysis/visualization. Familiar with NLP/NLU tasks and machine learning techniques, and experienced with many types of data: behavioral, eye-tracking, neuro-imaging, and language data. Strong background in formal linguistics (syntax, morphology, semantics) and experienced in language models.

## **SKILLS**

Programming Skills: Python, R, JavaScript Languages: Vietnamese (native), English (fluent)

#### **EDUCATION**

# **Johns Hopkins University**

Ph.D. in Cognitive Science 2019 – present 2018 - 2019M.A. in Cognitive Science

#### **Truman State University**

B.S. in Psychology and Cognitive Science, Minor in Statistical Methods. Valedictorian. 2013 - 2017

## RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

### Graduate Researcher, LANGUAGE ACQUISITION LAB, JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY

 $\overline{201}8$  – present

- First project: Investigated language acquisition using corpus data and computational linguistics
- Second project: Tested syntax theories using behavioral experiments and corpus analysis
- Third project: A non-parametric Bayesian model for clustering and classifying grammatical variants

## Lab Manager, Language Acquisition and Brain Lab, University of Delaware

2017 - 2018

- Conducted research on perception and learning using behavioral, eye-tracking and neuro-imaging techniques. Supervised 3 research assistants. Managed the lab's database and workflow
- Lead data analyst and programmer for the lab's computer-based experiments.
- Lead web developer for the online platform with multiple interactive tasks to collect behavioral data.

#### Statistical Consultant, Center for Applied Statistics & Evaluation

2015 - 2017

- Led a team of 3. Handled data analysis for several research projects and faculty grants
- Designed surveys and experiments, led focus groups, and generated statistical reports

#### Research Assistant, EEG LAB, TRUMAN STATE UNIVERSITY

2016 - 2017

- Conducted research on human perceptual processes (audio-visual integration) activity using EEG

## APA Summer Undergraduate Research Scholar, Texas A&M University

Summer 2016

- Conducted research on the aging brain using meta-analysis, neuroimaging and brain stimulation

# Academic Trainer, STEP SCHOLARS PROGRAM

2016 - 2017

- Tutored STEM subjects, including Computer Science, Mathematics, and Statistics.
- Graded homework for advanced statistics courses.

## **AWARDS**

•	Science of Learning Fellowship for multidisciplinary approaches in studying cognition	2020 - 2021
•	Graduate student travel award	Spring 2020
•	Dorothy Pearson Foundation Scholarship for outstanding students in Statistics	2016
•	Harold L. Hess and Ozella M. Hess Foundation Scholarship for academic excellence	2015
•	President's Honorary Scholarship for outstanding incoming students	2013
•	President's List x 8 semesters	2013 - 2017

## RELEVANT COURSEWORK

Computational Linguistics: Computational Linguistics; Computational Psycholinguistics; Human & Computer

Cognition; Intro to Human Language Technology

Computer Science: Object-oriented programming and design; Foundations of Neural Networks; Machine

Translation; Machine Learning – Deep Learning

Statistics: Statistical Computing; ANOVA; Linear Regression; Biostatistics; Advanced R

## **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **PAPERS**

- 1. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). Covert movement in English probing wh-questions. In *Proceedings of Linguistic Society of America 2020 Annual Meeting*. 5(1). 180-186.
- 2. Bernard, JA, **Nguyen**, **A**, Hausman, HK, et al. (2020). Shaky scaffolding: Age differences in cerebellar activation revealed through activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis. *Human Brain Mapping*. 2020, 1–27.

#### **TALKS**

- 1. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). Testing syntactic simplicity: wh-in-situ vs. fronted wh-questions in L1 acquisition. Talk at *Many Paths to Language, Max Planck Institute Conference*, Nijmegen, The Netherlands. Acceptance rate: **23.5%**
- 2. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. (2020). The acquisition of English wh-in-situ. Talk at the *Linguistic Society of America 2021 Annual Meeting*, San Francisco, CA. Acceptance rate: **35.2%**.
- 3. **Nguyen, A.** (2020). The acquisition of English wh-in-situ. *Brown Bag talk at the Cognitive Science Department, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD.*
- 4. **Nguyen, A.**, & Kozloff, V. (2017). Statistical learning and language. Talk at *the Experimental Group Meeting at the Department of Linguistics and Cognitive Science*, University of Delaware, Newark, DE.

#### CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

- 1. **Nguyen, A.,** Howe, W., & Legendre, G. (2020). English-speaking children's acquisition of wh-in-situ. Poster at *Generative Approaches to Language Acquisition North America* 6. Reykjavík, Iceland. Acceptance rate: **45%**
- 2. Weng, Y.L, **Nguyen, A.,** Ryskin, R., & Qi, Z. (2020). Prediction and sentence ambiguity resolution: A simultaneous eye-tracking and EEG study. Poster at *33rd Annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference*, Amherst, MA.
- 3. Schneider, J., Arnon, I., **Nguyen, A.**, Medez, K., & Qi, Z. (2019). Does prior language experience hinder statistical learning? Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 4. Schneider, J., Weng, Y., Kozloff, V., **Nguyen, A.**, & Qi, Z. (2019). Neural sensitivity to speech distribution information underlise statistical learning. Poster presented at *Neurobiology of Language*, Helsinki, Finland.
- 5. Qi, Z., **Nguyen, A.**, Ozernov-Palchik, O., Beach, S., May, S., Arciuli, J., & Gabrieli, J.D.E. (2018). Statistical learning in reading development and reading impairment. Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 6. **Nguyen, A.**, Sanchez Araujo, Y., Georgan, W., Arciuli, J., & Qi, Z. (2018). Re-examine the reliability of statistical learning tasks across domains and modalities. Poster presented at *Psychonomic Society Annual Meeting*, New Orleans, LA.
- 7. Kozloff, V., **Nguyen, A.**, Arciuli, J., & Qi, Z. (2018). Statistical learning in a noisy environment is associated with vocabulary. Poster presented at *Boston University Conference on Language Development*, Boston, MA.
- 8. Mendez, K., **Nguyen, A.**, Kozloff, V., & Qi, Z. (2018). The role of native language in statistical learning success. Poster presented at *University of Delaware's ninth annual Undergraduate Research and Service Scholar Celebratory Symposium*, Newark, DE.

#### MANUSCRIPTS UNDER REVIEW

- 1. Schneider, J., Arnon, I., **Nguyen, A.**, Mendez, K., & Qi, Z. *The relationship between statistical learning and prior language experience.*
- 2. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. Distinguishing among in-situ wh questions in English: echo versus probing questions.
- 3. **Nguyen, A.,** & Legendre, G. The acquisition of wh-questions: Beyond structural economy and input frequency.